Spending time on setting up the environment and installing tools before I can even start testing
is the part that I truly dislike.
Luckily, we have things like Kali Linux that comes with a bunch of tools pre-installed.
For web3, we have Ziion and today I'm joined by André from Halborn
who will show us how we can spend minimum time on setting up the environment for testing web3.
Enjoy!
Hello André, thank you so much for joining me today.
Today we'll talk about a set of tools that you've built for testing blockchain.
I struggled a lot when I was reproducing blockchain vulnerabilities
with all the setup steps, different blockchains and everything.
And from what I've heard, you created something that is supposed to solve all these problems.
Can you talk me some about it?
Yes, of course, Greg. Thank you for having me.
I'm the product owner of Ziion, which is a virtual machine
that includes all the tools necessary to do smart contract auditing.
You can have a chain in Solidity, EVM, Rust, Solana, Polkadot, Substrate.
We have all those protocols already integrated and all the tools to audit them.
Awesome. Sounds awesome.
So without further ado, can you show me how to find bugs with Zion?
Of course.
Okay, so we have the N1CTF 2022, which has already been solved and published.
So we are not going to spoil anything.
If you look, you have two folders. One is the server and the other one is the solve.
And then you have a script that simply compiles the solve and just runs it.
So if we look into the framework,
we can run low-hanging fruit tools, for example, to find vulnerabilities in the crate,
in the dependencies, or things like that.
We have Cargo audit, we have Cargo geiger for anything unsafe.
We have Siderophile for potential fuzzing targets,
even though a manual review is always better for this.
We have many other tools that are available, like Soteria, you have other things like that.
So let's do, for example, Cargo Audit.
And we'll see that it will find some vulnerabilities in the crates that this code uses,
which is pretty common, simply because you have dependencies that have some vulnerabilities
doesn't mean necessarily that your contract is insecure.
For example, you have this one, the time, which is a potential segfault,
which is quite high vulnerability, yet doesn't mean that you are vulnerable to it.
You have other ones, race conditions, etc.
But for each of them, you need to ensure that by checking the advisory,
that your contract is not vulnerable through the dependency.
Yeah, that's great. Tools are always good starting points.
But I imagine if it's not the most basic CTF task or in the work itself,
we do need to do manual analysis. Do we have some tools in ZIION to also do this?
Of course. So, yeah, in most contract audits,
this is just the first few tools that you run to get quick, low-hanging fruits
that are pretty standard into a report. But we have VS Code, actually VS Codium.
So that way it is open source and with a bit less tracking than the Microsoft version of VS Code.
You can see here by opening the CTF that you have a library.
You also have a main contract there.
And basically, most of the time of the smart contract auditor will be spent in Codium
doing manual code review because even though AI tools are big now, etc.,
nothing beats the human yet. So here you can see that you have a main program that is a server.
It is listening on the port 8080, creates a connection.
You can see that it initialized environment, mint some token and register an employee A,
for example, from the organization product.
It then deposits a thousand token, mints a thousand token and deposits 500 token into that account
for the employee A.
This is the account we don't have control over. Is it correct?
Exactly. This is the account that is created automatically by the program right now.
We have no access to it. We must create a new account.
Once the setup is done for that account, we have now the player account that has 100 tokens.
100 tokens is available to the player and the goal is to get more tokens, obviously.
How do we do it?
That's a great question. How do you find vulnerabilities in contracts in general?
First, you have to check the different functions of the contracts.
You can see that there are three main functions.
One is register function after the initialization, of course.
You can see that it requires the employee ID to be a certain length,
the organization to be a certain length too.
Then it ensures that this already exists. Otherwise, it is duplicated.
Otherwise, it says that it's a duplicate employee.
Then we have the deposit function.
Then we can deposit tokens to that employee.
You can see that it requires that the employee is already in the system
and it checks that the employee record, the organization and the ID is already there.
Then it does the transfer and it ensures that the vault amount is superior
to the amount that we are actually depositing.
Then you have the withdraw function.
Same thing, it does the checks to be sure that this employee exists.
It ensures that we can't withdraw more than what the vault has in the correct order.
It checks for the different seeds and then it withdraws.
If we go check the struct of those functions, you can see the register.
It registers into the catalog the seeds of the user.
It checks that that's the employee record.
Now we're in the struct for the deposit.
We see that they have initialization if needed.
It creates the account if it's not already created.
It seeds the account as organization name as bytes and employee ID as bytes.
What's a seed? What is it used for?
The seed is used for the creation of the PDA, which is a program-derived address.
Basically, in Solana, everything is an account.
The program has a PDA to do its bidding in terms of transfers.
You can see you have different constraints here.
The employee record must be the organization name and it must be also the ID.
We can't really fake the PDA.
We can't really fake the token itself.
There are some restrictions which prevent it to simply allow us to hack this.
If we run, for example, the script which simply runs the solve,
we can see that the player has 100 tokens.
That's our basic amount.
Right now, we don't have the flag or anything simply because we don't have more than 100 tokens.
In order to do that, we have to check how can we withdraw more without encountering those constraints.
The key here is in the way that the seed is generated.
The seed is generated simply with our name as bytes and employee ID as bytes concatenated together.
If we predict the seed, does it automatically mean we can withdraw money from a different account?
Withdraw tokens, sorry.
Exactly. We basically do some kind of seed collision by doing that.
You can see that the original seed when you look here is based on product and employee in the program by default.
To solve that, we need to reproduce this string, product and employee together.
Well, that's actually quite simple and at the same time a bit sneaky.
And also something that the automatic tools wouldn't find.
You simply need to first find the program address which is with that seed product employee.
And then into the solving program, which is here, you can see that that's where we are.
We have employee B and then our instructions go here.
Well, we don't want to be employee B. We want the funds from employee A.
Yeah, but there was a check for if employee ID is unique, no?
Actually, yes, it is. But the seed itself is what allows the transfer.
So here, if you change the strings to do this, it will work.
Or you can also simply do that and it will work because the seed in the end is the same when you add those two strings together.
Yeah, because there's a check if the employee ID is unique, but there's no check if these two things concatenated.
Exactly. And that's exactly why it is vulnerable.
So if we complete the withdrawal function, we saw how the struct is and what are the parameters.
I'm pasting here the different parameters for the account withdrawal, which is pretty standard there.
And here we're going to withdraw 500 tokens.
We could withdraw less if we want, but we know that this employee A has 500 tokens.
Here, I just save the files and you can see that there's an error here.
It's simply because we need to clone those variables because in Rust, you have to borrow or clone the different variables.
Now that it's saved, this is good. And if we run it, it should normally bypass the security and give us the flag, hopefully.
And as you can see, this time we have 600 tokens and the flag is flag.
That's awesome. That's great. And speaking of download Ziion, how does this work?
Is it the Docker image? Is it the virtual machine?
Where do people go to install this and basically start testing web-free vulnerabilities?
Sure. So we can download a VM directly. I will show you.
So we go to the website, we click on download, we choose the architecture that we want.
For example, Intel AMD, and we want from the VirtualBox one because that's what we have installed.
Double click on it, it launches VirtualBox. You can check the different parameters.
You can adjust how many CPUs or RAM you want to put to assign to this VM, for example.
And once that's fully imported, you can simply just start it.
That's simple and easy, just like I like it.
Yep. You simply double click on things and somehow it all happens.
Awesome. Looks really good. Thank you so much for joining me today and explaining to us how to use this.
I will definitely use it the next time I'm explaining or looking for web3 vulnerabilities.
For people, they go to ziion.org to install this. Is this correct?
Yes, it's correct. You go to ziion.org and you can click on the download button just as we showed earlier.
You can also register on a newsletter by going on to halborn.com and subscribing there.
We also have a blog on the ziion.org website, so you can check your content from time to time there.
Awesome. Thank you again for joining me today.
My pleasure. Thank you for having me, Greg.
If you're interested in web-free vulnerabilities, check out this video about a bug in Polygon blockchain that was rewarded $3.4 million.
For now, thank you for watching and goodbye.